Guide to the Catholic churches and organizations publications and ephemera 1986.016
Brooklyn Historical Society
Catholic churches and organizations publications and ephemera
1866-1976
Brooklyn Historical Society
Church of Our Lady of Perpetual Help (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Assumption of the Blessed Virgin Mary Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Brooklyn Catholic Historical Society
Church of the Sacred Heart (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
St. Michael-St. Edward's Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
St. Charles Borromeo Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Trinity Church (New York, N.Y.). St. Paul's Chapel
St. Patrick's Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
St. Boniface Parish (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Trinity Church (New York, N.Y.)
Our Lady Help of Christians (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
St. Francis of Assisi Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
St. Francis Monastery (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
1986.016
0.5 Linear Feet in one box.
The Catholic churches and organizations publications and ephemera consists of newsletters, bulletins, church histories, anniversary publications, programs from church services, and financial statements dating from 1866 to 1976.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was formally accessioned in 1986; source and date of the majority of the materials is unknown. When known, provenance is noted at the file level.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by name.
Historical note
From the mid-19th century to the present day, Catholics have remained the largest religious denomination in New York City. Catholic mass was first held in Manhattan in 1683, though parishes and churches were not established until the end of English persecution of Catholics, and after the American Revolution, in the late 18th century. In the then-village of Brooklyn, a Roman Catholic Society was founded in 1822, which oversaw the establishment of St. James' Roman Catholic Church in 1823. St. James', located on Jay Street in present-day Downtown Brooklyn, was the first Catholic church built on Long Island. The influx of European immigrants--especially Irish, German, and later Italian--lead to rapid growth of the Catholic church in New York City. To address needs of an increasing number of churches in Brooklyn, the Diocese of Brooklyn was established in 1853. It remains as of 2010 one of the most populous Catholic dioceses in the United States.
Sources:
Sharp, John K. History of the Diocese of Brooklyn, 1853-1953. New York: Fordham University Press, 1954.
Shelley, T. J. "Catholics." In The Encyclopedia of New York City, ed. Kenneth T. Jackson, 190-193. New Haven: Yale University Press; New York: New-York Historical Society, 1995.
Scope and Contents
The Catholic churches and organizations publications and ephemera consists of newsletters, bulletins, church histories, anniversary publications, programs from church services, and financial statements. Churches represented in the collection include Assumption of the Blessed Virgin Mary Church, Church of Our Lady of Perpetual Help, Church of the Sacred Heart, Our Lady Help of Christians Church, St. Boniface Church, St. Charles Borromeo Church, St. Francis Monastery, St. Francis of Assisi Church, St. Michael-St. Edward's Church, and St. Patrick's Church. Also included in the collection are issues of the Primitive Catholic newspaper as well as items from Franciscan Brother events in Brooklyn, the Brooklyn Catholic Historical Society, and Trinity Church in Manhattan.
Catholics -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Church history; Church finance -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Church anniversaries -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Church anniversaries -- New York (State) -- New York; Newsletters; Magazines (periodicals); Franciscans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Church bulletins; Financial statements; Catholic Church -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Programs (documents); Church of Our Lady of Perpetual Help (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Catholic Historical Society; Assumption of the Blessed Virgin Mary Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Church of the Sacred Heart (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); St. Boniface Parish (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); St. Michael-St. Edward's Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Trinity Church (New York, N.Y.). St. Paul's Chapel; St. Charles Borromeo Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); St. Patrick's Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Trinity Church (New York, N.Y.); Our Lady Help of Christians (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); St. Francis of Assisi Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); St. Francis Monastery (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- The Brooklyn Oratory of St. Philip Neri, 2018-2020 (Box 1)
  Historical note
  "Providing pastoral care for [the Church of the] Assumption of the Blessed Virgin Mary and St. Boniface."
- Catholic Historical Society, 1901 (Box 1)
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of Rev. John K. Sharp, date unknown.
  Scope and Contents
  One bound copy of Catholic Historical Society Records No. 1.
- Church of the Assumption (of the Blessed Virgin Mary), 1960, 2000-2021 (Box 1)
  One newsletter dated July 3, 1960 and several programs and bulletins from the 2000s-2020s.
  The Church of the Assumption is located in Brooklyn Heights on Middagh and Cranberry Streets.
- Church of Our Lady of Perpetual Help, 1909 (Box 1)
  One souvenir edition of the Mammoth Fair Official Bulletin.
- Church of the Sacred Heart, 1881, 1885 (Box 1)
  Financial expenditures, 1881; list of contributors, 1885.
- Downtown Brooklyn Parishes, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  Downtown Brooklyn Parishes consists of St. Michael-St. Edward and St. Boniface. "State of the Parish," 1975 and 1976.
- Franciscan Brothers, circa 1950s (Box 1)
  Centennial dinner program, 1959; "Day in the Life" booklet, circa 1950s.
- Our Lady Help of Christians, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  Several copies of the monthly "Church Bulletin."
- The Primitive Catholic newspaper, 1890 (Box OS-23)
  Two issues, September and November 1890.
- St. Charles Borromeo, 1924, 1960, 1974 (Box 1)
  Diamond Jubilee materials, 1924; Church Bulletin, 1960; Reunion program, 1974.
- St. Francis of Assisi, 1972 (Box 1)
  Several issues of the "Tell A View" parish newspaper, January-June 1972.
- St. Michael-St. Edward, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  "The Tower" newsletter, "State of the Parish," various programs.
- St. Patrick's, 1873-1874 (Box OS-23)
  One sheet detailing church finances.
- Trinity Church (Manhattan), 1880, 1946 (Box 2)
  "History of Trinity Church and its Graveyard," 1880; Ascension Day program, 1946.
- Trinity Church (Manhattan) - St. Paul's Chapel, 1866-1901 (Box 2)
  Centennial publication, 1866; "Recollections of St. Paul's Chapel" by Rev. Morgan Dix, 1867, inscribed by Dix to LIHS; "Old St. Paul's Chapel," 1896, gift of Frederick E. Haight; "Historical Handbook No. 1: St. Paul's Chapel," 1901, gift of Alfred T. White.